This is so much fun. They look so cute
in their little tutus. And then I went
to work one day and as I was walking in,
he was walking in and I said, "Oh, come
on, Peter." And he's like, "You know, I
thought you were a spy." And I said, "I
actually didn't think you were a spy."
And he was just going for a liaison
meeting.
And we had a good chuckle about it. And
I said, "Listen, don't tell anybody."
Right. Right. Right. Right. Sorry.
So, I'm trying to figure out how many
how many spies do you think there are in
the United States? If you think about
>> foreign spies,
>> foreign spies, domestic spies, people
that are basically undercover,
>> including Americans, you mean?
>> Including Americans.
>> The number of CIA employees is
classified. The number of CIA employees
undercover is actually even more highly
classified. I can give you a guesstimate
>> but also you know Russia, China.
>> Yeah. 50 to 60,000 altogether.
>> 50 to 60,000 in the United States.
>> So by a couple of degrees of separation
if you know a 100 people.
>> Yeah. You're probably going to know one.
>> Sure.
>> You said there's probably about 50,000
in the United States. So I've just done
some quick math on my notepad here.
which means that in order to know one,
[clears throat] you'd need to meet 6,600
people.
>> Okay.
>> Because the US population is roughly 330
million people.
>> That's right.
>> And I and then I did some other maths
and did some research and I asked
[laughter]
um the question I was trying to figure
out is how many people does the average
person meet a year?
>> And it's roughly about 3 to 10,000
people.
>> [clears throat]
>> So theoretically,
>> so the chances are good
>> every year.
Statistically,
according to my napkin math, you're
meeting one of these undercover spies.
One a year.
>> There it is.
>> Now, that number I gave you is I'm
lumping like all CIA people and all
foreign intelligence officers in the
United States.
>> Interesting. But again, if you work for
an American defense company, Northrup,
Grumman, Lockheed Martin, Boeing, any of
them, your chances of encountering a
foreign intelligence officer are even
money.
>> Can't you as a spy with the United
States ask the United States to give you
loads of money? Like, can't you say,
"You really want me to go do that? Can I
have a million dollars?"
>> Cuz you're giving you're potentially
giving away a lot of money to other
>> Oh my god. giving away like unlimited
amounts of money
>> because your budget when you were a spy.
How much was it
>> after 911? It was unlimited.
>> What does that mean? It means you can
basically give away as much money as you
need to.
>> If I approach somebody and he says I can
give you
this terrorist. I want 10 million. I'm
like [clears throat] done.
>> What was the most you ever gave in
>> 10 million?
>> You gave someone 10 million for what?
>> Abu Zabeda.
>> Who's Abu Zabeda? We believed that Abu
Zubeda was the number three in al-Qaeda.
He wasn't the number three, but he was a
very bad guy. I led the raids that
captured Abu Zuba in Pakistan, Fisalabad
Pakistan in March of 2002.
And um
the State Department had a $10 million
reward. We ended up giving the 10
million to the Pakistani intelligence
service. It wasn't
>> a person
>> a person. [clears throat] It was just
really great analysis that led us to
him. But there were others in the
so-called war on terror
who
got more than 10 million and got it like
within 24 hours.
>> Individuals.
>> How much?
>> One got 25 million.
>> Just a person.
>> Uh-huh. And the thing is, you know,
there's a lot of danger there. If you're
a if you're a, you know, a shepherd or a
tea boy
and you make $40 a month and all of a
sudden you have $25 million,
something's up.
>> And what was the 25 million for?
>> It was for a very high ranking
foreign terrorist who was brought to
justice. I I can't I can't say because
it was never
publicly disclosed. But what we would
have to do in a situation like that is
we would have to tell the the source,
you can't live here anymore. Pick a
country and that's going to be home from
now on. And then we go to that country
and say, hey, can you do us a solid?
We've got this guy who, you know, he
really came through and he's not going
to be a burden on your economy
>> cuz he's got $25 million.
>> Which country did he pick?
>> Oh, I can't I can't tell you that.
>> He wanted He wanted to stay in the
region. He He wasn't willing to move to
the United States, for example,
>> cuz we're happy to take him. You're
welcome to come to the United States.
He's like, absolutely not.
>> You went to Dubai.
>> I would.
>> Yeah. With the tax code. [laughter]
Interesting.
H
I think I'm I think I'm Yeah, I'm You
can tell my bias from the questions that
I ask about the things that fascinate me
about espionage and spies is just it's
the un their understanding of human
nature and what motivates us and the
psychology of humans that you can learn
from um spies and the nature of human
beings I guess,
>> right? And also, I guess the thing that
really fascinates me is just
I've had so many mind mind-blowing
moments where I've learned just how
fragile the reality that I believe is.
Like I thought things were secure and I
thought they were as they are, but
>> right,
>> it just doesn't appear to be that way.
There appears to be lots of secrets.
>> And you know, conspiracy theorists get a
hard time, but actually the more I've
done this as a job, the more I go, hm,
conspiracy theorists are right more than
I expected them. And that's an important
point.
I [sighs]
>> I hate conspiracy theories that run a
muck, but you know, the the the a former
CIA director is the one who came up with
the term conspiracy theory.
>> And it was it was a way for the CIA to
discredit people by making them sound
like crazy people when in fact there was
such a thing called MK Ultra. There was
such a thing called, you know, operation
grasshopper or or MK Chickwit or, you
know, the CIA did crazy crazy stuff from
roughly 1952 to 1975.
For example, they um experimented with a
a virus
that they
that they released in San Francisco.
They waited for an unusually foggy, like
heavily foggy day. They released it into
the atmosphere just to see if it would
make people sick. And 11 people went to
the emergency room with this rare upper
respiratory infection. And then they
were like, you know, high fives. Yeah,
it works. And then they they started
experimenting with LSD. LSD was a big
thing at the CIA in the early days. We
were convinced. See, and this this is
this is where counter intelligence is
important.
The Chinese
told us in like 1951
that the Russians were using LSD to try
to engineer it to be used as a mind
control drug.
That wasn't true. That was
disinformation. The truth was the
Russians had no LSD program. The Chinese
did.
So they tried to throw us off the off
the scent by blaming the Russians.
We panicked and by 1952 we started this
program called MK Ultra which began by
using LSD
um experimentally.
What the CIA did was they they started
by dosing their own employees without
telling them.
Um, several committed suicide. One
jumped out of a hotel window
>> with the hope that
>> yeah, we'll just see what happens. See
what they say. See how it feels, you
know, see if we can control them. See if
we can plant memories that didn't
actually happen. And then they decided,
no, it's not a good idea to dose our own
people. Let's just dose strangers out in
public. So they went to San Francisco.
They
rented a safe house and they hired
prostitutes to go out on the street,
pick up John's, bring them back to the
safe house.
>> John's
>> John's people who hire prostitutes, men
who hire prostitutes,
dose the John's with uh LSD and just see
what happens.
But I mean these are like serious
crimes you're committing against people.
>> Just reading about it here. It says
under Operation Midnight Climax.
>> Interesting name. Operation Midnight
Climax, the CIA paid sex workers to lure
men to safe houses where agents drugged
them and then watched them through
oneway mirrors and recorded their
behavior.
>> Exactly.
>> They tried to erase their personality.
Nice, huh?
>> The goal was often to break and rebuild
the human mind. In 1973, the CIA
director ordered mass destruction of the
MK Ultra files. What we know comes from
accidentally surviving documents,
meaning this is a sanitized version.
>> That day, he testified before the church
committee. The church committee
specifically told him, "Do not destroy
any documents." He went back that
afternoon to the CIA and said, "Destroy
everything."
>> Why? Because it it was damning. They
were experimenting on American citizens.
They were they were experimenting by
spreading diseases in American cities.
And so
he was held in contempt of Congress. He
was fined like $150
and um about 15% of the documents were
overlooked and survived.
We'll never know exactly what happened